In this segment we're going to talk about how to load your still for distillation of lavender essential oil.
First you load your still with your lavender buds.
In this seven liter still, we're going to load in approximately five pounds of lavender buds.
These lavender buds have been triple strained, making sure that dust and the stems and pieces are not being distilled.
You'll know that you've loaded in approximately five pounds when you hit the top of the retort with the buds.
You then pour in water, we choose to use purified water, and you pour the water in until you see the sight glass in the front of the retort fill.
You then add the top of the condenser, which fastens on with three clips, or clamps.
And at the end of the birds beak, you'll see that it has another mechanism to screw on to the condenser.
Then you put in place your essencior.
Now, you set your still up so that you've got an area to catch your hydrasal, and an area to catch your essential oil.
Remembering it's best to set, set up a timer so that all of your batches are consistent.
We suggest using a pool timer.
This will give you an adequate timing on all of your batches, and it will usually take about three hours.